Guide to the Pare Lorentz papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
- Series I: Ecce Homo, 1938-1942, undated
  - Subseries 1. Correspondence, Scripts, and Research, 1938-1942, undated
    - Stackpole Sons, 1939 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Research
      - 1938-1940, (2 Folders) (Box 3, Folder 8 to 9)
      - Government Machinery, 1938 (Includes Photos) (Box 3, Folder 10)
      - Hold The Man, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 11)
      - "Men, Methods and Machines," 1939 (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - Relief Material, 1938 (Box 4, Folder 2)
      - Unemployed Compensation Form, 1939 (Box 4, Folder 3)
      - Unemployment, 1939 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Name, Age and Occupation
      - Script, 1942 (Box 4, Folder 5)
      - Early Treatment, 1941 (Box 4, Folder 6)
      - Notes, 1942, (2 Folders) (Box 4, Folder 7 to 8)
      - Press Clippings, 1941-1942 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Subseries 2. Shooting Notes and Selected Takes, 1939-1942, undated
    The shooting notes in this subseries document the shot-by-shot progress of production.
    - Name, Age and Occupation
      - Shooting Notes, 1942 (2 of 3 Folders) (Box 4, Folder 10 to 11)
      - Shooting Notes, 1942 (1 of 3 Folders) (Box 5, Folder 1)
      - Record of Negative and Positive, 1948 (Box 5, Folder 2)
      - Estimating Script, 1942, (2 Folders) (Box 5, Folder 3 to 4)
    - Ecce Homo
      - Selected Takes, undated, (2 Folders) (Box 5, Folder 5 to 6)
      - Shooting Notes, 1939 (Box 5, Folder 7)
      - Shooting Notes--Prod 3, 1938-1939, (3 Folders) (Box 6, Folder 1 to 3)
  - Subseries 3. Still Photographs, circa 1938-1942, undated
    Some of the still photographs depict the actors and filmmakers at work. But the majority consists of 8x10-inch shots, mounted on cardboard, depicting scenes from across the Midwest during the Great Depression. The images, most of which were taken by Edwin Locke, focus on industrial production, cityscapes, streetscapes, and landscapes. They were used as research for the film.
    - Name, Age and Occupation--Photos of Leads, undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Decatur, Indiana, undated (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Ecce Homo
      - Ed Locke Photos, undated, (5 Folders) (Box 6, Folder 6 to 10)
      - Location Shots, undated, (2 Folders) (Box 6, Folder 1 to 12)
      - Stills, undated (1 of 5 Folders) (Box 6, Folder 13)
      - Stills, undated (4 of 5 Folders) (Box 7, Folder 1 to 4)
      - Still Pictures--Cast, undated (Box 7, Folder 5)
      - Carded Stills--North, undated (Box 7, Folder 6)
      - Carded Stills--IV, undated (Box 7, Folder 7)
      - Carded Stills, undated, (2 Folders) (Box 7, Folder 8 to 9)
      - Carded Stills, undated, (4 Folders) (Box 8, Folder 1 to 2, 4, 6)
      - Carded Stills--Alternates, undated (Box 8, Folder 3)
      - Carded Stills--Alternates V, undated (Box 8, Folder 5)
      - Carded Stills--P. 84, undated (Box 9, Folder 1)
      - Carded Stills--P. 85-86, undated (Box 9, Folder 2)
      - Carded Stills--P. 86, undated (Box 9, Folder 3)
      - Carded Stills, undated (Box 9, Folder 4)
      - Carded Stills, undated, (6 Folders) (Box 10, Folder 1 to 6)
      - Carded Stills, undated, (5 Folders) (Box 11, Folder 1 to 5)
      - Carded Stills--Industrial America, undated (Box 12, Folder 1)
      - Carded Stills, undated, (3 Folders) (Box 12, Folder 2 to 4)
      - Carded Stills, undated (includes Pare on location) (Box 12, Folder 5)
      - Carded Stills, undated, (5 Folders) (Box 13, Folder 1 to 5)
      - Carded Stills, undated, (5 Folders) (Box 14, Folder 1 to 2, 4 to 6)
      - Carded Stills--The Proffet and the Picket, undated (Box 14, Folder 3)
      - Carded Stills--Selected by Robert L. Snyder, undated (4 of 6 Folders) (Box 15, Folder 1 to 4)
      - Carded Stills--Selected by Robert L. Snyder, undated (2 of 6 Folders) (Box 16, Folder 1 to 2)
    - Name, Age and Occupation--Negatives, undated (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - Ecce Homo--Oversize Album, undated (Box 17, Folder 3)
- Series II: The Fight For Life, 1921-1942, undated
  Lorentz’s last major completed film, The Fight For Life is the story of the Chicago Maternity Clinic, a progressive but under-funded healthcare facility that achieved heroic results for Chicago’s working-class families. The movie features three professional actors, but the rest of the people who appear are patients and nurses of the center.
  - Subseries 1. Distribution, Publicity, Research, 1921-1942, undated
    This subseries contains notes and records related to the film’s screenings in various cities. There are many press clippings, mainly movie reviews.
    - Correspondence--Actors, 1939 (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - Advertising, 1940 (Box 18, Folder 2)
    - Columbia Pictures, 1940 (Box 18, Folder 3 to 4)
    - Contract and Copyright, 1939-1940 (Box 18, Folder 5)
    - Camera Report, 1939 (Box 18, Folder 6)
    - Continuity, 1940 (Box 18, Folder 7)
    - Distribution, 1940 (Box 18, Folder 8)
    - Research, 1940 (Box 18, Folder 9)
    - Distribution Returns, 1940 (Box 18, Folder 10)
    - Distribution--Noncommercial Requests, 1940-1941 (Box 19, Folder 1)
    - Fan Letters, 1940 (Box 19, Folder 2)
    - Harcourt, Brace and Co., 1938-1940 (Box 19, Folder 3)
    - Medical Controversy, 1938-1940 (Box 19, Folder 4)
    - Interoffice Memos, 1940 (Box 19, Folder 5)
    - Music and Musicians, 1939-1941 (Box 19, Folder 6)
    - Publicity, 1938-1940 (Box 19, Folder 7)
    - Radio, 1940 (Box 19, Folder 8)
    - Previews, 1940 (Box 20, Folder 1)
    - Pass List, 1940 (Box 20, Folder 2)
    - New York Premiere, 1940 (Box 20, Folder 3 to 4)
    - Prints and Production, 1939-1940 (Box 20, Folder 5)
    - Special Exploitation, 1940 (Box 20, Folder 6)
    - Publicity, 1940 (Box 20, Folder 7)
    - Publicity, 1939-1942, (2 Folders) (Box 21, Folder 1 to 2)
    - Stills, 1940 (Box 21, Folder 3)
    - Sound Record, 1940 (Box 21, Folder 4)
    - Research--Birth Control, 1939-1940 (Box 21, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence--A-D, 1939-1940 (Box 21, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence--G-L, 1939-1940 (Box 21, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence--M-R,1939-1941 (Box 22, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence--S-W, 1939-1941 (Box 22, Folder 2)
    - Research Materials, 1938-1939 (Box 22, Folder 3)
    - Interdepartmental Committee, 1938 (Box 22, Folder 4 to 5)
    - Birth Reports, undated (Box 22, Folder 6)
    - Research Materials, 1938-1939 (Box 22, Folder 7)
    - Research Materials, 1938-1939 (Box 23, Folder 1)
    - Gruenberg Compositions, 1921-1923 (Box 23, Folder 2)
    - Research Materials, 1938-1939 (Box 23, Folder 3)
    - Maternity Publications, 1933-1939, (2 Folders) (Box 23, Folder 4 to 5)
    - Doctor’s Organizations Contact Information, undated (Box 24, Folder 1)
    - Background Notes, 1939 (Box 25, Folder 1)
    - Research Materials, undated (Box 25, Folder 2)
    - Chicago Maternity Center, 1939 (Box 25, Folder 3)
    - Maternity Center Bulletin Board Records, 1936-1939 (Box 25, Folder 4)
    - Statistics, 1939-1940 (Box 25, Folder 5)
    - Research Publications, 1936-1940 (Box 25, Folder 6)
    - Research Publications, 1936-1940 (Box 26, Folder 1)
    - Research Materials, 1935-1938 (Box 26, Folder 2)
    - Screenplay, 1939 (Box 26, Folder 3)
    - Shooting Scripts, undated (Box 26, Folder 4)
    - Reviews, 1940 (Box 27, Folder 1)
    - Publicity, 1940 (Box 27, Folder 2)
    - Reviews, 1940 (Box 27, Folder 3)
    - Script and Research, 1939 (Box 27, Folder 4)
    - Research, 1938 (Box 27, Folder 5)
    - Publicity, 1939-1940, (2 Folders) (Box 28, Folder 1 to 2)
    - Publicity, 1936-1940 (Box 28, Folder 3)
  - Subseries 2. Production, 1939-1940
    These files contain extensive documentation of the production process. The production script notes were removed from their original binders.
    - Script Notes
      - Production 4--Volume 1, 1939, (2 Folders) (Box 186, Folder 4 to 5)
      - Production 4--Volume 2, 1939, (2 Folders) (Box 29, Folder 1 to 2)
      - Production 4--Volume 3, 1939 (Box 29, Folder 3)
      - 1939-1940 (Box 29, Folder 4)
    - Complete Scripts, undated (Box 29, Folder 5)
    - Scene Notes, 1939 (Box 29, Folder 6)
    - Script Notes, undated (Box 29, Folder 7)
    - Publicity, 1940 (Box 30, Folder 1)
    - Shooting Script, undated (Box 30, Folder 2)
    - Screenplay, undated (Box 30, Folder 3)
    - Script Sheet--Chicago Notes, 1939 (Box 30, Folder 4 to 5)
    - Script Sheet--Hollywood Notes, 1939 (Box 31, Folder 1 to 2)
    - Hollywood and Chicago, 1939 (Box 31, Folder 3 to 6)
    - Scene Notes, 1939 (Box 32, Folder 1)
    - Exploitation, 1940 (Box 32, Folder 2)
    - Script Notes Production 4--Chicago, 1939, (3 Folders) (Box 32, Folder 3 to 5)
    - Shooting Sequences, undated (Box 32, Folder 6)
    - Shooting Script Report, 1939 (Box 32, Folder 7)
    - Shooting Script Report, 1939 (Box 33, Folder 1)
    - Code Book, undated (Box 33, Folder 2)
    - Negative Camera Reports, 1939 (Box 33, Folder 3)
    - Lloyd Nosler, 1939-1940, (2 Folders) (Box 33, Folder 4 to 5)
    - Financial Record, undated (Box 33, Folder 6)
    - Public Health Service, 1939 (Box 33, Folder 7)
    - Daily Journal, 1937-1938, (2 Folders) (Box 34, Folder 1 to 2)
    - Daily Journal, 1939, (3 Folders) (Box 34, Folder 3 to 5)
  - Subseries 3. Stills, undated
    Some of the still photographs filed here were taken on set, others come from the film itself, and a third group was used by Lorentz for research while he was writing the screenplay.
    - Mounted Stills, undated (Box 35)
    - Mounted Stills, undated (Box 36)
    - Mounted Stills, undated (Box 37, Folder 1)
    - Stills, undated, (4 Folders) (Box 37, Folder 2 to 5)
- Series III: The Plow That Broke The Plains, 1935-1942, undated
  The Plow That Broke The Plains was Pare Lorentz’s first effort as a director. A half-hour-long documentary with orchestral music and a portentous narration, the film dramatizes the plight of American farmers and extols the efforts of President Roosevelt’s New Deal. The film was made under the aegis of the Resettlement Administration – the name would soon change to the better-known Farm Security Administration – an ambitious agency that hoped to encourage farmers to move from dust bowl areas to ecologically stable land. The film premiered in March 1936, in a special presentation before Roosevelt in the White House.
  - Subseries 1. Publicity and Clippings, 1936-1941, undated
    After initially struggling to generate enthusiasm for his film, Lorentz eventually packed his picture into suitcases and traveled the nation, appealing directly to reporters and theater owners. These reviews and feature stories, clipped from newspapers and magazines, are the result of that effort.
    - Posters, 1936 (Box 38, Folder 1)
    - Clippings, 1936-1941, (5 Folders) (Box 38, Folder 2 to 6)
    - Rural Rehabilitation in Region One, 1937 (Box 39, Folder 1)
    - Press Releases--Region 1, 1935-1938, (5 Folders) (Box 39, Folder 2 to 6)
    - Press Releases--Region 2-5, 1936-1937 (Box 39, Folder 7)
    - Press Releases--Region 7-8, 1936-1938 (Box 40, Folder 1)
    - Press Releases--Region 9, 1936-1938, (2 Folders) (Box 40, Folder 2 to 3)
    - Press Releases--Region 11, 1936-1937 (Box 40, Folder 4)
    - Information for the Press, 1936-1937 (Box 40, Folder 5)
    - Minutes and Memoranda, 1936-1938 (Box 40, Folder 6)
    - Weekly Information Memos, 1937-1938 (Box 40, Folder 7)
  - Subseries 2. Production and Distribution, 1935-1942
    These folders contain booking forms and records, notes on distribution.
    - Financial Records, 1935-1936, (2 Folders) (Box 41, Folder 1 to 2)
    - Old Plow Bills, 1936-1937 (Box 41, Folder 3)
    - Lorentz Plow Travel, 1935-1936 (Box 41, Folder 4)
    - Bookings--Commercial, 1936-1938, (2 Folders) (Box 41, Folder 5 to 6)
    - Bookings--Commercial, 1936-1937, (2 Folders) (Box 42, Folder 1 to 2)
    - Bookings--Non-Commercial, 1936-1937, (3 Folders) (Box 42, Folder 3 to 5)
    - Bookings--Non-Commercial, 1936-1938, (4 Folders) (Box 43, Folder 1 to 4)
    - Bookings--Reports and Distribution, 1936-1937, (2 Folders) (Box 43, Folder 5 to 6)
    - Bookings--Reports and Distribution, 1937-1939 (Box 44, Folder 1)
    - Distribution, 1936-1939 (Box 44, Folder 2)
    - Foreign Distribution, 1936-1937 (Box 44, Folder 3)
    - Confidential Report, undated (Box 44, Folder 4)
    - Fan Mail, 1936 (Box 44, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence--Edwin Locke, 1940 (Box 44, Folder 6)
    - Description of Scenes, 1935 (Box 44, Folder 7)
    - General Information, 1935 (Box 44, Folder 8)
    - Notes on Purpose and Production, undated (Box 44, Folder 9)
    - Memos and Correspondence, 1936-1942 (Box 45, Folder 1)
    - General Information, undated (Box 45, Folder 2)
    - Study Guide, undated (Box 45, Folder 3)
    - Ecological Map, 1935 (Box 45, Folder 4)
    - Shooting Script, undated (Box 45, Folder 5)
    - Requests, Prints, Previews, 1938-1939 (Box 45, Folder 6)
    - Music and Narration, undated (Box 45, Folder 7)
    - Regional Information, 1936 (Box 45, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence--Washington, 1936-1937 (Box 45, Folder 9)
    - Publicity, 1936-1939, undated, (2 Folders) (Box 45, Folder 10 to 11)
  - Subseries 3. Stills, 1935, undated
    The stills in this subseries include photos of the crew working on location.
    - Stills, 1935, (2 Folders) (Box 46, Folder 1 to 2)
    - Carded Stills, undated, (4 Folders) (Box 46, Folder 3 to 6)
- Series IV: The River, 1935-1943, undated
  In June 1936, Lorentz pitched the idea for his second film, The River. In his original conception, the documentary would follow a single drop of water as it flowed from the source of the Mississippi to the Gulf of Mexico. Along the way, the words and images would depict the social, ecological, and economic life of the Mississippi Valley, which at the time was home to more than half of the nation’s population. Later, he scrapped the original idea of tracing the river’s length and instead based the action around the tributaries flowing into the main stream. One of the main themes of the film is humanity’s careless stewardship of the river, which had led to serious erosion and flooding. The first screening was held in New Orleans in October 1937.
  - Subseries 1. Printed Materials and Publicity 1936-1940, undated (Box 46)
    This subseries contains press reviews, distribution materials, shooting record from production and screening.
    - Paramount Reports From Exchanges, 1938-1939, (4 Folders) (Box 47, Folder 1 to 4)
    - The Land, 1939-1940 (Box 47, Folder 5)
    - Movie Making Ideas, 1936-1939 (Box 47, Folder 6)
    - U.S. Government Films, 1938-1939 (Box 47, Folder 7)
    - Postaudit and Claims, Letters, 1937-1940 (Box 48, Folder 1)
    - Budget, 1935-1937 (Box 48, Folder 2)
    - New Orleans Voucher, 1940 (Box 48, Folder 3)
    - Miscellaneous Pieces Re: The River, 1938 (Box 48, Folder 4)
    - The River, signed by Franklin and Eleanor Roosevelt, 1935-1938 (Box 48, Folder 5)
    - Publicity, 1937 (Box 48, Folder 6)
    - The River, a U.S. Documentary Film, undated (Box 48, Folder 7)
    - Publicity Book, undated (Box 48, Folder 8)
    - Press Information, undated (Box 48, Folder 9)
    - Venice Film Festival Award, 1938 (Box 49, Folder 1)
    - Grand Shorts Award, 1938 (Box 49, Folder 2)
  - Subseries 2. Subject Files, 1935-1943
    These folders contain research materials used by Lorentz to write the screenplay and choose locations.
    - General Information, 1938-1941 (Box 50, Folder 1)
    - Australia, Mervyn Scales, 1938-1940 (Box 50, Folder 2)
    - Biographies, undated (Box 50, Folder 3)
    - Book, The River, 1937-1938 (Box 50, Folder 4)
    - Booking, 1938-1939 (Box 50, Folder 5)
    - Booking Reports, Griswold Summaries, 1936-1938 (Box 50, Folder 6)
    - Booking Reports, Commercial Paramount, 1938-1939 (Box 50, Folder 7)
    - Booking Reports By State, 1938-1940 (Box 50, Folder 8)
    - Bookings, Balaban and Katz, 1937 (Box 50, Folder 9)
    - Bookings, Boston Opening and Run, 1937-1939 (Box 50, Folder 10)
    - Bookings, Cameo Theater, 1938 (Box 50, Folder 11)
    - Bookings, Special, 1938-1939 (Box 50, Folder 12)
    - Brief Synopsis of The River, undated (Box 50, Folder 13)
    - Cameramen For The River, 1937 (Box 51, Folder 1)
    - Canadian Showings and Requests, 1938-1939 (Box 51, Folder 2)
    - Commercial Appeal Article, 1937 (Box 51, Folder 3)
    - Contract, Paramount, 1937-1940 (Box 51, Folder 4)
    - Copyright, 1938 (Box 51, Folder 5)
    - Criterion Opening, 1938 (Box 51, Folder 6)
    - Cutting Continuity, 1938 (Box 51, Folder 7)
    - Distribution Statistics, 1939-1940 (Box 51, Folder 8)
    - Distribution, March-July 1939- January-June 1940, (3 Folders) (Box 51, Folder 9 to 11)
    - Distribution--Foreign, 1937-1940 (Box 52, Folder 1)
    - Distribution--Migrant Camp Movies, 1938 (Box 52, Folder 2)
    - Distribution--Non-Commercial, 1937-1940 (Box 52, Folder 3)
    - Distribution Policy, 1938 (Box 52, Folder 4)
    - Distribution Requests--Commercial, 1937-1938 (Box 52, Folder 5)
    - Fan Mail, 1937-1939 (Box 52, Folder 6)
    - Location Trip Diary, 1936 (Box 52, Folder 7)
    - Location Background, 1937 (Box 52, Folder 8)
    - Lorentz Coast Trips, 1937-1938 (Box 52, Folder 9)
    - Mississippi Premieres, 1937-1938 (Box 52, Folder 10)
    - Education Plan, 1938 (Box 52, Folder 11)
    - Exchange List, 1939 (Box 52, Folder 12)
    - Griswold, 1937-1939 (Box 52, Folder 13)
    - Financial Report, undated (Box 52, Folder 14)
    - Exploitation--Regional Information Advisers, 1938-1939 (Box 52, Folder 15)
    - Exploitation--Magazine and Other, 1937-1938 (Box 52, Folder 16)
    - Exploitation--Radio, 1937 (Box 52, Folder 17)
    - Miscellaneous, 1937-1940 (Box 52, Folder 18)
    - Music, 1937-1938 (Box 53, Folder 1)
    - Music and Copyright, 1938 (Box 53, Folder 2)
    - Payrolls, 1937-1938 (Box 53, Folder 3)
    - Permission to Use Title of The River, 1937 (Box 53, Folder 4)
    - Personal Appearances, 1937-1938 (Box 53, Folder 5)
    - Press Book, 1937 (Box 53, Folder 6)
    - Press Book--Paramount, 1937-1938 (Box 53, Folder 7)
    - Press Releases--NY Office, 1938 (Box 53, Folder 8)
    - Press Reviews, 1937-1938 (Box 53, Folder 9)
    - Clippings, 1937-1943 (Box 53, Folder 10)
    - Research and Production, 1935-1937 (Box 54, Folder 1)
    - Zone Reports and Activities, 1937-1938 (Box 54, Folder 2)
    - Previews, 1937-1938 (Box 54, Folder 3)
    - Prints, 1938-1939 (Box 54, Folder 4)
    - Questionnaire and Answers--Little Red School House, undated (Box 54, Folder 5)
    - Releases, 1938 (Box 54, Folder 6)
    - Research Data--Production #3, 1937 (Box 54, Folder 7)
    - Service Manual, 1938 (Box 54, Folder 8)
    - Stills, 1938-1943 (Box 54, Folder 9)
    - Technical Production Costs, undated (Box 54, Folder 10)
    - Television, 1938-1940 (Box 54, Folder 11)
    - Venice Exposition, 1938 (Box 54, Folder 12)
    - Verbatim Transcript From Movie, undated (Box 54, Folder 13)
    - Washington Premiere and Run, 1937 (Box 54, Folder 14)
  - Subseries 3. Still Photographs, 1935-1940, undated
    Some of these are stills from the movie, while others were used for research.
    - Stills--"A", undated (Box 55, Folder 1)
    - Stills--"B", undated (Box 55, Folder 2)
    - New York City, undated (Box 55, Folder 3)
    - The River, 1940 (Box 55, Folder 4)
    - Pare Lorentz On Location, 1936 (Box 55, Folder 5)
    - Complete Set 10 Paramount Stills and 18 Rejects, undated (Box 55, Folder 6)
    - Publicity Stills--L8-L27, undated (Box 55, Folder 7)
    - Publicity Stills--L28-L60, undated (Box 55, Folder 8)
    - Publicity Stills--1-10, undated (Box 55, Folder 9)
    - Publicity Stills--11-20, undated (Box 55, Folder 10)
    - Publicity Stills--22-29, undated (Box 56, Folder 1)
    - Publicity Stills--30-47, undated (Box 56, Folder 2)
    - Publicity Stills--48-55, undated (Box 56, Folder 3)
    - Carded Stills, undated (Box 56, Folder 4)
    - Still Photographs, undated, (3 Folders) (Box 56, Folder 5 to 7)
    - Still Photographs, 1935-1938,undated, (6 Folders) (Box 57, Folder 1 to 6)
    - A Complete Set of 10 Stills, undated (Box 57, Folder 7)
    - Still Photographs, undated, (6 Folders) (Box 58, Folder 1 to 6)
- Series V: Other Films, 1938-1969, undated
  This series contains materials related to some of Lorentz’s other film projects.
  - Subseries 1. The City, 1938-1941
    Stills and correspondence related to The City (1939). Lorentz wrote the screenplay, but the picture was directed by Ralph Steiner and Willard Van Dyke, both of whom had previously worked with Lorentz as cinematographers. The film was commissioned by the American Institute of Planners and first aired at the 1939 World’s Fair in New York. Like earlier efforts, The City had a message. In this case, it was the perils of city life. It stressed the purity of rural and village living and stressed the beneficial effects of increased suburban housing.
    - Correspondence, 1938-1941 (Box 59, Folder 1)
    - Scripts, 1938-1939 (Box 59, Folder 2)
    - Research, 1937-1938 (Box 59, Folder 3)
    - Clippings, 1939-1941 (Box 59, Folder 4)
    - Stills, undated (Box 59, Folder 5 to 6)
  - Subseries 2. Nuremberg Trials Film, 1947-1969
    In 1946, the Allied Control Council agreed to produce a documentary film on the Nuremberg Trials. Two million feet of captured German film were scattered through the United States. Lorentz took responsibility for compiling the footage into a coherent whole. He created a 75-minute film, entitled “Nuremberg – Its Lesson Today.” Shown in commercial theaters in the U.S. Zone in Berlin, to great acclaim, it was pulled from circulation when the Cold War changed the focus of American foreign policy. Materials include correspondence, clippings, and a “brief explanation” of the project.
    - Prospective Investors, 1950-1951 (Box 60, Folder 1)
    - H. William Fitelson, 1951 (Box 60, Folder 2)
    - Lists of People to be Invited to Showings of Nuremberg Trials Film, 1950 (Box 60, Folder 3)
    - Prospectus, 1950-1951 (Box 60, Folder 4)
    - Covington et al., 1948-1956 (Box 60, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence, 1949-1964 (Box 60, Folder 6)
    - Nuremberg Trials Film, 1949-1969 (Box 60, Folder 7)
    - The Nuremberg Trials, 1948-1952 (Box 60, Folder 8 to 9)
    - United Nations, 1950-1951 (Box 60, Folder 10)
    - Clippings, 1949-1956 (Box 60, Folder 11)
    - Nuremberg--Brief Explanation, 1949 (Box 60, Folder 12)
    - Nuremberg, 1947-1951 (Box 61, Folder 1 to 2)
    - Trial of the Major War Criminals, 1947 (Box 61, Folder 3 to 5)
  - Subseries 3. Good Neighbors, 1939-1941
    Lorentz envisioned this as “a gentle comedy” about the relations between North and South America. He hoped to work with Cantinflas, whom he described as “the greatest star in Latin-America.” Materials include correspondence, clippings, and distribution plans.
    - Cantinflas and Pare Lorentz Working Together, 1941 (Box 61, Folder 6)
    - Distribution, 1939-1941 (Box 61, Folder 7 to 8)
    - Distribution, 1939 (Box 62, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence and Clippings, 1941-1942 (Box 62, Folder 2)
  - Subseries 4. Polio, 1948-1951
    A screenplay Lorentz wrote on the behest of the National Foundation for Infantile Paralysis. The files consist of correspondence and research, as well as screenplay drafts.
    - National Foundation for Infantile Paralysis, 1949-1951 (Box 62, Folder 3)
    - Screenplay, 1949 (Box 62, Folder 4)
    - NFIP--Major Research, 1949 (Box 62, Folder 5)
    - NFIP--Miscellaneous Research, 1949 (Box 62, Folder 6)
    - NFIP--Film, 1948 (Box 63, Folder 1)
    - NFIP--Roughs, 1949 (Box 63, Folder 2)
    - Polio and its Problems by Roland H. Berg, 1948 (Box 63, Folder 3)
    - Screenplay Drafts, 1948-1949 (Box 63, Folder 4)
  - Subseries 5. Other Films, 1930s-1963
    Some materials related to other film projects, including The Land, My Brother’s Keeper, and The Face of the Earth, an environmental documentary.
    - The Face of The Earth, 1950-1963